all right hello and welcome everyone it
is July 8th
2024 and we're in active inference art
stream number 2.1 a computational model
of aesthetic value with
anman and we'll have a presentation
followed by a discussion so thank you
very much for joining to you for the
presentation and looking forward to
it um thanks so much for having me
Daniel I'm really really thrilled to
talk about a computational model of
something that a lot of people still
doubt that machine models can ever
attempt to model um namely aesthetic
value and that's been the work I've been
doing for a couple of years and today I
don't necessarily want to talk so much
about the concrete content of this model
which I do a lot with my papers and it's
just as important I think what's also
important and often gets left out a bit
from the conversation is the question of
why we should even bother um developing
and applying a computational model to
something so complex as aesthetic
valuation right so this is going to be a
really high level overview and I'd be
really stoked if we could have the
discussion about this because that's
really what I'm trying to instigate
here so stuff that I want to talk about
is that it Valu is grandiose words with
a rather intuitive but also quite fuzzy
meaning what I'm talking about
personally when I talk about aesthetic
value is something actually quite
mundane it's the pleasure that we derive
from any sort of sensory experiences and
you all have felt that value and acted
according to it when you decided to go
to a concert or listen to song when you
went out into the mountains or any sort
of landscape and just gazed at it um
when you went out to a restaurant and
decided what you want to eat and savored
that taste or even when you touched
something or someone and it just felt so
good you wanted to touch to linger all
these experiences of pleasure that are
based on the sensory properties of the
object to interact with I personally
call aesthetic value
and my mission for a couple of years has
now been to find a computational model
that can tell us something about how
these values emerge and what they do to
our
Behavior to answer that question the
most important foundation to me
personally is to ask the inherently
computational question um if we take
it to the original meaning of the
computational of what this so-called
aesthetic value is there for what does
it do why do we have an emotional
effective reaction towards sensory
properties and in the past people have
come up with two very different families
of theories to explain these
Origins um one of them um I will in
short D fluency theories are very much
about what I would call Lazy brain
saying that aesthetic value actually
indicates to us that we are easily able
to process the sensory stimuli and our
brain likes that because it needs to do
less work in a sense to simplify
horribly um and examples where that has
shown up in the data is when we look at
symmetric stimul so only on half as we
process or when we look at the effects
that we get from familiar or exposure so
the more often we see something the more
we tend to like it and that might
according to fluency be because we get
to be able to process it more easily
becoming more familiar with
it and this is very much a evaluation of
the present moment how good am I right
now in dealing with my sensory
environment this theory has very often
been criticized for being overly
simplistic and not very much looking
into the future because it's so grounded
in the present moment and so in came a
different family of theories that I will
summarize under an umbrella term of
learning theories um that very much rest
on the assumption that aesthetic value
is actually a signal for learning so not
so much present moment adaptation but
rather a look into the future gauging
how well the current sensory environment
can serve me in learning about the
future sensory environment as well this
is all about making inferences about
recognizing errors in our perceptions
and then reducing them so the value here
comes from a reduction of processing
errors of errors in making predictions
about sensory
environment um and in that sense we
striving to adapt for better adaptation
into the future so both theories have
one big thing in common and that is the
underlying goal here is to make sensory
perception processing good with
different emphasis on the present moment
in terms of fluency and the long-term
future when comes to
Le when I discussed the theory with my D
supervisor Peter Dean we were both kind
of struck by the simple question about
these theories Would we not want to have
both would we not want to simultaneously
be good at processing your world as it
currently is as well as learn about
potential
future so the model that we came up with
wants to achieve both goals concurrently
um and has to weigh off between the two
so the sensory system striving to both
recognize what is in front of it right
now but also wanting to predict as best
as possible what is going to encounter
in the future um and you see that in
everyday life too right so if you want
to work with your sensory system just
crossing the street you want to both now
be able to recognize what is in front of
you do I know this person should I greet
them but you also want to be able to
make accurate predictions about whether
or not that car is going to hit you the
next second if you do proceed to cross
the
street and this is a very very prominent
theme throughout most models of machine
learning um that are based on theas of
reward learning there is an agent that
right now decides its next action based
on what is rewarding in this very moment
willst taking into consideration whether
its predictions and the action that
resulted from that led to better RSE
outcomes than expected so predicting the
future evaluating it right now and then
adjust
Behavior
accordingly and what we I I believe is
why should the sensory system and the
value that comes from that this
aesthetic value be any different from
those with that thought in mind we
proceeded on um building that but what
does it look like so just taking one
step back for those people here who have
not kind of sat in front of their
computers and actually done something
with these things this is what a
computational model looks like it's it
is just a bunch of code it's a bunch of
mathematical formulas realized in any
programming language you like um and you
can run it on simplified comput computer
representations numbers of the things
you want to simulate and derive
predictions from it um and this
particular one for athetic value is
implemented and you can download it from
GitHub and I very much try to keep that
updated what is key for its usefulness
for people like me and I'm a
psychologist by training is that these
Expressions the definitions and the
terms using them um are interpretable
right so every function here um serves a
as a proposed mechanism Um this can be
very high level but it can in other
cases go down to the functions of
individual neurons that are being
modeled here um
most often though we see this
interpretability in the parameters that
are passed onto these functions so what
are the settings under which these
mechanisms operate and that is true in
this particular model as
well what our model does to gain this
interpretability is that it has two sets
of functions that interact with each
other two parts of the model that do
roughly represent this one famar
theories of processing fluence
and it also has one that represents the
mechanism that um represents learning
from prediction errors that gives reward
for prediction error reduction
so this looks like
in
a sorry one
second there was my speakers going up um
my headphones going out um and we can
repres Us in in a comic like way right
where we can actually at least in a
simplified one-dimensional structure
represent what the model looks like so
it is nothing more or less than um the
representation of the expectations of
the inner system so a probability
distribution of what the system expects
to see right here right now and it takes
a readout of that probability so what
are my predictions in terms of what we
see here is we look at a dog one
relevant feature of the dog is how long
is its fur we have an expectation of how
long it is we read out how well the
current environment meets our
expectations and that read out is one
component um so this is one of the
functions that lets us know um the
reward that we get out of here the value
from immediate processing fluency right
now and we can do a similar thing um
illustrating how learning Works in this
model how we actually bring in the first
component of learning by shifting our
expectations um as you see here by shift
in the distribution according to what's
present right now so I see a dog with
long fur hence I expect dogs to have
longer fur um also expressed as a
function and we can go on and then say
okay how do I represent errors how can
my current state of beliefs be in
contradiction to an expected future and
so we can simulate that by saying we
have a mechanism that evaluates how
different is my current expectation to
my expectations of the future and we can
then over time evaluate how these
long-term expectations match up to the
current learning process and whether the
learning in by itself gets us closer to
long-term expectations or removes us
further from them and that term then
gives us what we call a reward of
learning is the development of the
prediction error over
time
um and that I horribly gloss over and
I'm super happy to give you more details
but I really wanted to get to this one
very important Point like telling OKAY
computational model is nothing fancy
what is important is the idea that
stands behind it and how we real ize
it but as just as important to me as a
researcher who very much does Empirical
work
is ideas are good and well but does it
do anything and that's what I was very
happy to work on with my master students
where we put took the model implemented
in computer code and
said can it actually produce something
produce predictions that are anything
like the behavior we see for people
people um and here we looked at one
particular finding first with
simulations that we know very well very
many Studies have looked at it it's
called A Mir exposure effect and it's
depicted here on the left hand side and
it basically looks at how much people
like or enjoy something on the Y AIS as
a function of how often they've
experienced it and what we usually see
is an inverted U-shaped curve where up
to a certain point more exposure more
familiarity leads to more liking but
eventually this trend is going to turn
on itself and we get bored and our model
as you can see from the overlapping
lines um comparing the data to the
model's prediction is indeed able to
replicate these findings and its
settings so its parameters and how
they're expressed um can tell us
something about how this effect came
about and again glossing over the
details here very happy to talk about it
later but it basically gives us a
constellation um a geometry of settings
that allow for this effect to occur and
much very importantly discards all other
options um and most um surprisingly to
me what a model could do very well is in
a completely separate experience
experiment with our own data it was able
to predict individual people's judgment
on how much they liked images um very
well on an individual trial by trial
level so we could say for individual
trials that the model never saw in the
sequence what a participant would grade
them solely based on their other
responses um so the model was indeed
able to mimic something that was able to
produce the same responses as humans
would do and again Our Hope here is not
to say oh great now we can build the
best you know recommendation algorithm
for any um internet platform you could
imagine based on such a model um what we
are excited about is that the parameter
settings behind us tell us something
about where these judgments actually
came
from um and this model performs better
than other more naive model so what you
see here is a comparison um on the y-
axis of the error that our model makes
versus on the xais something that um is
very often so used in Psychology namely
the assumption that everybody responds
like everybody else on average and that
always makes way greater um errors in
predicting people's responses than when
we take a more complex but
individualized approach to things and
that's very reassuring for
us um yes so it does do more than these
more naive methods in the sense that the
difference in the parameters suggest
reasons for differences so what is so
very often said about how we um do our
evaluations of aesthetic experiences
that they're in the eye of the beholder
there's now something to a back up that
these are not coincidental and be
something that suggests where they might
be coming
from and I think there's even more we
can do with this kind of approach to
even a subject as pzy and sometimes hard
to study as aesthetic valuation right so
we can test different variations of this
model against each other we can leion
the model right so we're not hurting
anyone here we're just removing parts of
the code um and see which elements of
the model are indeed essential to its
functioning um and again find out more
about the possible mechanisms that are
indeed involved and crucial to this
process um we can and this is to me
exciting as somebody um who does not
come from the computer science world uh
or the machine learning world now
compare this model to what I mentioned
in the very beginning the same
architectures were employed for decades
to teach machines how to learn and um to
understand why rats exhibits um certain
behaviors right it's the same
architecture what does that imply about
aesthetic valuation as a reward learning
model um and because it is so similar to
the reward learning models that underly
um Machine Vision um and a lot of the
deep convolutional neural Nets we're
using to process sensory stimuli most
often visual to translate them into
machine language we have a rationale to
use these highly potent image processing
architectures and use them to quantify
what is in those images also in our
research
um and it offers the possibility to
simulate right so we can now make
predictions before we even start an
experiment about what people should do
if our models were correct if we have
one like
this um and I will end this here for
this particular presentation um and I'd
be super sted to start a conversation
with
you all right
awesome
cool okay lots of ways to uh go I'm
looking forward to discussing it and if
anyone watching has a a question then
they can type it and I'll ask it um
let's just start with how did you come
to be studying this intersection of
questions and methods and and
theoretical perspectives
give me one second to put out my alarm
that has been started ringing in the
background um it's an amazing
question
so as I think for many people my journey
started a little bit coincidental so I
was initially very interested going to
arts school but was very much
dissolution so I've always been very
interested but di athetics in the
broadest term I play instruments I paint
I draw um and had a supervisor who very
randomly asked me whether I would want
to study that but as a psychology
PhD and that supervisor already was in a
place both in terms of colleagues as
well as his own personal history um that
bound him very closely to computational
methods so I studied at NYU with Dennis
P who is a mathematician by training and
the psychology department there is very
fond of very quantitative um methods and
building their own models to explain how
the world works and that's how my
journey started and this perspective has
never been forced on me but it's the one
that I was brought up with and I always
found it very very useful for the
reasons that I just said um in terms of
being able to integrate a
field that is often a bit separated
right there's a lot of people by now
doing research on aesthetic experiences
but often very removed from the rest of
the world um and I always thought well
why not talk to the people we are
talking about visually appreciating
things so it's got to do something with
how the entire visual apparatus works
right so why not use the methods of
those people who do the more cognitive
or quote unquote basic side of things
and apply them to this more effective
evaluative side of
things um and then and and Via that I
became really interested in
computational modeling because I started
realizing
that experiencing beauty or pleasure
from something is not just something um
that is a nice you know it's it's not
icing on the cake off life it's very
ingrained in everything we do really
especially in the industrialized Western
World so I became very interested in
this question how does this influence
our decision making why do we you know
spend a couple of hundred dollars uh and
a lot of time and effort to travel
somewhere to watch somebody play music
for two hours right it doesn't make any
sense and then I went to tubing worked
with Peter Deon who is somebody who's
worked on reward learning models um
comput very deeply computational models
for very many say and I came to him and
said I have a hunch that these models
apply to what I've been doing for five
years too are you willing to work with
me on that and luckily he said
yes cool thank you yeah it's interesting
that Aesthetics seems to sit in a way
between perception and behavior and also
philosophy in that it's a a often seen
as a philosophical area however one that
deals quite explicitly with the
perceptual system that might be
addressed by psychology
otherwise um okay you mentioned
interpretability so that was in the
context of the computational modeling H
how do you think about interpretability
of aesthetic models when we have this
kind of dual interpretability from the
inside like our own interpretability of
the underlying phenomena and then we
have this kind of external
interpretability whether that's
observing somebody having aesthetic
experience or doing modeling like how
how far can we get with interpretability
and what does that look like
here yeah that was a really good
question so I think probably the
furthest we
can go and anesthetics that might be a
long way off is you know linking model
components to physiological biological
reality and being concretely able to
say this function represents one neuron
this function represents you know how
signals are transmitted along the axon
and so on and so forth right they really
pinpoint every bit of the model to
something that is both functionally
important and physically
observable um but to me
interpretability in the state a Statics
at is the best when
each parameter in the model relates to
something that is part of the theory
that underlies it um so that when the
parameter changes or becomes irrelevant
that is probably the most crucial one we
we have justifiable reasons to change
our Theory or adjust it right so what in
our model for instance we have two
parameters that weigh the two components
um against each other so one parameter
scales how important the um value is
that is derived from this immediate um
fluency signal and the other one scales
how much value we derive from the um
prediction error reduction from the
reward of learning right and so if we
see consistently over time that we can
set one one or the other to zero and
nothing much happens that very clearly
indicates that one component of the
models is frankly Obsolete and doesn't
play a huge role and that to me is very
valuable interpretability in that
sense interesting so we saw the inverted
U exposure curve are there
phenomena that kind of buck that Trend
or are there maybe pieces or genres
where we have like a step like we enter
into it and then we can see more or
different like how do we account for not
just Rel listening 25 times to the song
but you know 2500 times to the
song yeah yeah it's one of my my
favorite things to ponder about as well
um so there are different ways that I've
discussed it with uh different
colleagues and I believe that we someday
might you know break it down to our
internal models just having slightly
different
settings but perhaps the easiest
explanation for it is that there's some
stimuli that just sit so very firmly at
the center of our expected future
beliefs right so that there's basically
never a negative learning experience
from them they are the Prototype of what
for this type of stimuli at least we
expect the world to be and remain
forever more um and so that then leads
the model to predict not an inverted U
shape uh but an ASM toote so you
basically stick around with very high
Pleasures throughout and it never goes
down
um that's the easiest way of explaining
it the more
um everyday explanation if if you will
one that we cannot test as easily in a
lab setting is that um we never listen
to the same song 25,000 times in a row
without anything else getting in the way
right and if that is the case you know
we can always kind of swing back with
our expectations and then come come back
to it kind of with a reset so it's not
that it's continuous exposure to the
same thing all over again but each time
you come back to that song you've
changed a little bit your expectations
have changed a little bit and so you're
learning a
new and if it sits at the right place of
your expectations about the world you're
always learning something good and so
you continue this infinite Loop Vias
short intermission
of being exposed to things that are you
know less enjoyable make you unlearn
something that was actually
beneficial H that's very interesting
it's like a Smelling Coffee cleansing
the palet and then relearning oh that I
like that food but also I'm kind of
relearning it um I I was also es
especially when when you connect the
fluency theory of Aesthetics to the
expectations I was struck that there's
the expected free energy construct for
decision-making and it has this
pragmatic value element of preferences
expectations and then the epistemic
value with the learning and so initially
I was wondering well aesthetic value
which is what motivated the um
Talk would Aesthetics be a third
elements in the consideration um or it's
it's almost more interesting that it
exists across these two areas of
expectations and that has more of an
archetype of being like well it's this
time so we hear this song so that's the
kind of like pragmatic side of
Aesthetics with a cultural scaffolding
of expectations and then there's also
this learning intrinsic
novelty element so it kind of comes down
just like action selection in the
general case it comes down to these kind
of two complementary but but
non-convertible
types of of impact that the stimuli can
have yeah I think you exactly captured
the intuition of that um it is debatable
whether that is all the there is twoips
and I personally do not think so I think
this model does a very good job at
capturing these two aspects um but you
know the more I think about it of course
the more incomplete the model becomes um
so yes I think there are these two
archetypes of also aesthetic enjoyment
I've also seen that across other
completely other theories like not not
psychological theories of Aesthetics
right there's this kind of um Cinema pop
culture entertainment aspect of oh this
is easy and comfortable um and then the
more challenging you know Fine Arts
aspect of Aesthetics and I do see both
of these discussed um both jointly and
independently uh what I think in terms
of selfism although the model is still
lacking is um maybe that's what you
meant with
aesthetic is a
contextualization in terms
of the sensory system does not exist in
isolation in our brains it is also um
coupled with everything else so elements
of nostalgia um of Association of of
memories that is something the model
completely disregards it just doesn't
have it baked into it um and so it's
completely and entirely possible we're
missing an important ingredient
St but again you know you cannot only
leion mod you can also amend it you can
add another component to it so if
anybody's up to could be very
thrilled cool yeah looking for those
like residuals or looking at what
factors matter where the model doesn't
predict well I I was I was definitely
thinking about um in light of that sort
of pop art and
decoration on through more like
epistemically challenging art sometimes
the they they what changes isn't
necessarily the medium but often is sort
of like the contextualization like the
music mum setting you're about to be
walking into this room where this is
going to be there and then the object as
the sort of um recent Decades of of art
have have shown like that object can be
anything and nothing and so then that is
like wasn't this about perception but
then what is there to perceive in this
blank wall yet also that becomes kind of
like the exception that proves the rule
because it it it starts to tap into the
more contextual elements and and
possibly reveal greater differences
amongst people rather than something
that that like um a ratio that strikes
many as pleasant due to deeper priors
about shape
yeah yeah no definitely and you know you
you can try and fit that into the model
too you know you can go ahead and that's
what we we maintain where it might
continue to be useful is that um context
might bring about a drastic shift in
parameter settings right so as soon as I
go into the museum I'm no longer looking
for something that is immediately easy
to process right now I'm voluntarily
getting myself into a context where I
know that there's more value to be found
in learning and challenging myself and
so that might be one way of saying okay
that's how you know we can
think of the model and not only modeling
differences between individuals because
that's how it does that too for instance
but also between
contexts um that being said there's also
completely different shifts that might
be more difficult to explain with that
um my most recent example is um it's
reping me as a bit of a nerd but the
author of The Dragon Ball series
recently died and I think along with a
lot of other people I Revisited
something from my childhood
is without that lens added to it wasn't
very good art to begin with but got a
different kind of appreciation for it
with like an whole back layer of
appreciation and historical
importance and whether that is just
parameter shifts that happen kind of
snap in an
instant I don't know so maybe we're
still missing
something yes Nostalgia and memory and a
given stimuli having like a pragmatic
value simply because it was learned to
be
expected and so then it all things being
equal is more likely to be part of the
expectations going
forward just part of the historical
learning
um okay so you mentioned um probably a a
a a illusion that that must be included
in every such talk about beauty in the
eye of the
beholder and yet what is in the eye of
the beholder is in the mind of the
beholder with their generative model so
H how would you say like predictive
processing predictive coding active
inference how are these cognitive
theories stepping into Aesthetics in the
modern era and like helping
reform or or
reinforce some of these more ancient
sentiments on
perception I think in recent times um
predictive coding has very much
reinforced first the notion of Beauty
and the eye of the beholder because it
in a sense offers a very easy
explanation to so as as to why there is
so much subjective variability with the
notion that you
know objectively
what the world gives to us in terms of
physical stimulation is not what
everybody experiences right it's an
active constructive process perception
is not something passive that just
happens and so for everybody it creates
something different so it should be
logical then that we also appreciate
things
differently however I think it's a very
healthy development in that with
predictive coding much as with other
models including all the computational
models it's not this story of hopeless
oh well we everybody's different so what
we're going to do about it now we can't
explain it possibly it offers
very good theoretical foundation for
understanding differences not as a
nuisance or measurement error but as
something that's that's actually at the
heart of the process itself right um I
think that's quite promising and I think
also in that sense that kind of
scientific approach to Aesthetics
receive much
more um positive feedback and welcoming
from the more artistic Community because
it does not want to take away from
differences does not want to explain
them away as Nuance but very much takes
them seriously as um something that
is a Justified
result of the underly
processes thank you yeah that's very
interesting like the account of the
painting is not seeking to explain away
the differences in shading or color the
account of different people looking at
the painting also would not want to
explain those away but rather like
account for the
distributions as they are and continue
the investigation um so you mentioned
algorithms how would you say your work
interfaces with like algorithms and
recommend ations especially in a era not
just of recommendation of extance
content but generative and synthetic
methods I mean personally this model
represents pretty much everything that
these algorithms want to do right it it
does not have a generative part yet but
it's architecture makes it blatantly
obvious how the generated part should be
constructed right you can construct a um
General adversarial Network out of this
no problem you could train it um in a
tener model with what we have right now
and you know if you have enough data
sure you could do it the only thing
that's not feasible about it is you
would have to have complete surveillance
over people and a good way of getting
continuous output about their reactions
and then you you could have um every
platform stream you know kind of
continuously predicting what's that
person going to like best next um and
that's kind of scary in in that sense
right um but I also think it's
hopeful in the sense that what current
algorithms are doing is really not
taking the to any consideration at all
so at the heart of the model as we have
it lies learning and lies the fact that
we do not want to be stagnant right we
do not want the same experiences over
and over and over again we do get bored
the exposure effect does eventually turn
negative um and in that sense offers
also always due to it not being this one
comic I showed but
multi-dimensional always many options of
what you know would as next experience
be rewarding and be valuable to you
um and in in that sense I always want to
kind of build the model out in that way
because it would get away from the
current State ofth art which is very
much cluster
driven putting people into okay you're
this part of the cluster you know okay
so you like rock so you probably like
hard rock and maybe country rock let's
try that okay you didn't like that maybe
you're more of a hard rock person and we
keep you firmly um and only recommend
you artists in that corner instead of
making a
jump um so
yeah I think everybody who works with
artificial intelligence in whichever
capacity these days kind of has to ask
this question right what is what is the
benefit what's the worst case scenario
and and in what way could it be helpful
and that's the
I could come up with so
far it's it is a dark but
fascinating like aesthetic pen Opticon
with the
biomarkers and the processing happening
faster than the time scales of our own
aesthetic judgments and then like
updating with recommendations or with
tweaking and
modifying in in in ways that that we
don't necessarily even see but then it's
like but what if that journey is taking
us on these epistemic flights and what
if the learning rate is being calibrated
to a kind of sensation um that couldn't
be provided like by people making arts
for each
other and I wonder if that will be one
of the Technologies or or kind of
manifestations that that will really
clearly highlight that contextual
element because very Salient stimuli
will be arising from that kind of a
process and then also there's going to
be like the drawing that my friend made
for me on the refrigerator which is like
static but then it's going to have this
embeddedness and the
connection and and then maybe that's
going to still be a thing to look at
yeah absolutely I think this is also I'm
not a doomsday Sayer when it comes to um
this ties into creativity a lot in my
opinion right so what can we gain from
generative art in any way sense and I
not want to say it's all doom and gloom
and it's all bad um but what you just
mentioned is kind
of embedding of a work into a personal
history be it with the viewer or with
the artist that we as viewers can then
learn about is something that you know
kind of goes beyond the scope of what
we're
doing um these days where you know our
modeling is very much reliant on
quantifying the objects and then trying
to infer what is going on inside the
view we're not quite there yet where you
know we also kind of infer the
underlying non-physical properties of
the stimulus itself beyond what is
provided by the viewer as well but maybe
one day in the future you know we're
going to have it solved and Aesthetics
is going to be Tri trivially solved
asid um H H how would
you represent the um the the
philosophical or psychological or
computational developments on
art recognition models in contrast with
models of creating art or different
Medias and different ways of more
actively constructing
art it's a really good question I
think they're approached right now from
two very
different um groups of people um so
everything I think that we see these
days in terms of um generative
approaches comes
from um and and I say that as a daughter
of an engineer um comes from Engineers
people who are very product focused
right who want to
give have an output that can be
practically used for something and as
such a lot of by now very impressive
Black Box models have emerged that can
produce things that are very impressive
like 20 years ago nobody would have
guessed that we could would be able to
do this but without any real
understanding of how that emerged from
you know tens of thousands of example
images that it was trained
on on the other
hand these people have become less
interested something that is also still
being done um that is modeling people's
responses um so these algorithms are
mostly really not good because they
don't have enough data and not good not
high enough quality data um the best
data sets you can get for training a
model to um on a large machine scale
model is from like an old page from a
photo contests um there like five or so
votes per image which for psychology
psychologist sounds like horrible
horrible horrible sample size the
horribly biased sample um and so these
efforts I
think by now have to stand back to what
is now more coming from the um cognitive
Sciences from psychology Neuroscience um
and those models are very different
because their predictive quality is
often not quite as good like they're not
as correct as
[Music]
um models would you know 10,000 of times
of parameters but they're very
interpretable um so I think there are
two very different worlds that also want
to do very different thing one wants to
deliver a product and the other one
wants to deliver more of an
explanation that's making oh go ahead
yeah and and the sad thing is I would
very much love to see them you know come
together but I don't see that quite
happening
yet
H that that's making me think about um
again with
interpretability and the um our own
observation of observing art or creating
art and what factors we feel are
associated with our own perceptual
experiences and our own generative
experiences like a funny quotation from
William Blake he said the difference
between a bad artist and a good one is
the bad artist seems to copy a great
deal the good one really does copy a
great deal and yet then I hear that the
kind of synthetic methods that we have
today are like glorified autocomplete or
copying which kind of even scales back
the conversation to like
but then would that still be art and
potentially even more artlike or would
that somehow make it less art
like and that conversation about what
makes something aesthetic what makes
something decorative versus high art how
are these longer term Trends in what is
perceived or or discussed as art that is
just like instantly we're just like back
in the whole fabric of of society and
the complexity and the uh uh and the
challenge of coming up with a neat
account of like any
phenomena yeah absolutely and it feels
like we're back in you know 18 19th
century with that really reminds me this
entire debate that we're having right
now you know is this art oh my God what
is happening to Art and artists at all
it reminds me very much of T when
photography was invented in a way
um it feel feels like de is
U repeating itself in in variations
which also art loves to do right
repetition in variation um and so I
guess I took the easy way out with that
in my Approach right really saying I'm
not even interested if you call it art
I'm also not very interested if you call
it aesthetic um very much interested in
what you feel when you experience that
and what that feeling makes you do and
then I I Love My Philosophy colleagues I
really do I love working with them but I
leave it absolutely up to them to
discuss defin semantics and terminology
of when exactly that crosses the border
from pretty to beautiful to aesthetic to
transformative I'm perfectly F sitting
here saying I I can at least predict
that they're going to they don't like
it h how how do you think about that
like reported
unreported
revealed question like is there another
kind of information or way that you look
at what people say in light of other
data yeah I mean the way that I
interpret your question is you know what
do we do with this play of psychology
when it comes to these very subjective
experiences of you know how do we
interpret what we're getting in terms of
data right that where getting
at um so my ideal that I strive towards
and I do have data that is just not good
enough yet right didn't think it through
a th% is looking at people's behavior
and make inferences from these behaviors
because um if we only observe for
instance the setup was like this
um how long people will look at a given
image before they decide that they want
to go on to the next
one they do not really need to think
about what we want them to say and they
don't really need to think about oh
what's going to tell you about me that I
say I like this image very much or not
um because there's concrete behavioral
consequences for them in the right here
and right now if they display a certain
action so you know um I can give them a
fine art piece uh and if I ask them to
rate this and they recognize it and
they're like oh yeah okay this is a
museum I should probably like this
otherwise I'm horribly uncultured it's
very easy to do that right there's no
negative consequences for them to
experience whether they Mark a one or
nine on a 1 to 10 scale who cares but if
I say listen I'm going to leave you here
for 10 minutes um and the only thing
you're allowed to do is look through
these images
um then there's the real consequence of
looking at this fine art piece and you
know deciding oh maybe should I really
look I really really don't like looking
at this but I I should like it right
and that's probably a better method but
it's also harder to pull off right so I
do think behavior is harder to set up
but if set up right the better more
direct measure of what's actually going
on
but for all intents and purposes
self-report as long as you do not give
people a reason to want to distort their
reports is probably the most direct and
easiest to do um and we are really lcky
in Aesthetics right like we do these
kinds of experiments mostly with stuff
that people are very happy to do right
we all love to talk about our favorite
music and our favorite movies and we
like to give our
opinions about these things they're
important to us so we can do self-report
easily it's just not perfect never going
to
be interesting also that that like in a
way recapitulates the kind of epistemic
foraging or optimal foraging type
experiments like there's 100 trees they
have different quality and then you
could just from the movement
patterns eventually parameterize a model
like to what extent was the switching
Behavior driven by saturation of
learning versus saturation of of the
preferences and then here it's again
that aesthetic
value has elements and then your model
is like like
a
Cornerstone for adding in some other
consider ations but um at minimum it it
fuses those two threads of theory and
gives the kind of minimal playground to
to start to explore like how those work
and and also how those might work in
Minds very different than humans like
looking at the response curves for
training neural
networks absolutely and Bo oh boy have I
been sitting through like I can't tell
you to how many workshops and stuff I've
been going on foraging behavior and
trying to do that um and and then I got
hung up on
boredom that's how it sometimes goes
right and then then we discovered this
thing about getting bored about things
and interestingly boredom wasn't boring
at all to think about and so I got
sidetracked but I think what you said
right about now is it also so cool to
start thinking about and again just
making these
connections um with foraging Behavior
because honestly when I pick up my my
phone and decide what music I want to
listen to for my bus ride to the office
that's kind of exactly what's going on I
have this limited time window to get
hopefully maximum enjoyment out of um
and it's exact just like do do I keep
digging in this corner of songs or like
is it more rewarding now to kind of
start something new and it's exactly
that that problem so yeah that's yeah
yeah it could be people in the museum
like the physical location the diffusion
and then there could be like um
different I mean it's it's like a
resource
location and um but it's very complex
there's there might be like a more
visible so then that's where like that
sort of like social thumb on the scale
of Aesthetics but then maybe somebody's
Aesthetics concept includes like
performativity at which point then
there's it's not it's not a um illicit
ad mixture to have the social value like
standup comedy or some other kind of
performativity where having other
people's gaze is part of what is being
constructed whereas in other kinds of
art there's like I mean even evidenced
by earlier in our um discussion like
there's a feeling like we could isolate
it to the viewer or to the
experiencer but then that is is almost
shown to be kind of like a a contrived
case not the natural history of how the
art is made and
used yeah absolutely and that that kind
of I think it's also goal that other
people are are working towards right now
what you mentioned is that these
single agent models that we all very
much rely on these days is also not
telling the entire truth of the
experience right um it not just my this
entire social component as well if we're
talking about these kinds of real life
settings and experiences that also bring
in their F to the completed
picture
yeah um okay in the last little bit if
if anyone wants to write a question they
can otherwise H how do you see your work
and research and everything unfolding or
what ways are you excited to
go
same my dream for all of this really is
to get a lot of people excited and
trying out these kinds of models um of
course for me personally most exciting
thing would be people picking up what
I've been doing and tweaking it and
really thoroughly testing it and
figuring out what is wrong with this
model because I'm sure there's something
wrong and getting to a very solid core
understanding of how it all sort of
relates today I've painted very much a
picture of what has um basic
visual but also other perception to do
with the valuation of these
experiences but that can be tied up so
much further into how do these EV these
valuations then impact our behaviors how
do these behaviors lead to changes of
the
experiences um and really take seriously
this idea
that there is no passivity in the
perception
of our world it's all a very much active
process that keeps on
changing um and I think we can get a
good understanding of that and I think
we're very exciting times um especially
for Aesthetics
to build these models in such a way not
only that they can be useful tools but
really give us a good understanding of
what aesthetic experience truly is so I
hope to be able to continue working on
that for very many years to
come awesome that idea of no
passivity kind of period is a big theme
in active inference and it it makes me
revisit the beauty in the eye of the
beholder and about the is
secting and about how with with gay
tracking the dwelling could be
associated with our like a local Maxima
looking at at a interesting feature of
an architecture or a specific location
and then the Cade pattern which few if
any people can directly control is
driven by epistemic
gain and that's this kind of like
hierarchical locking in like there been
a lot of experiments in active inference
with
facial recognition and faces that are
the right side up and upside down and
the kind of
epistemic trajectories that are
taken so maybe that's one way that um
predictive processing also like revisits
and enriches the beauty in the eye of
the beholder because it it it brings
action into that eye instead of just to
to be hold as a passive process that
would be like well you know the images
in the lens of the
photographer would be a passive stance
but then even even the I which is kind
of like a
symbol or has a connotation of of
receptivity but of course its action is
is so active and and ceaseless even on a
simple scene and then maybe even
um mysterious art like a solid color
square that then becomes like this
playground for The
cading and so that's like a kind of
experience
that start starts to um be revealing so
that's kind of
interesting yeah it also really H
understand something and really
emphasized today too what you said about
di really you know with their behavior
actively changing what we do perceive um
is that in line with learning also
always comes this notion of things being
Dynamic and basically due to technology
technological Advance we finally at that
stage where Aesthetics can hopefully
also move away from this okay we show
you athetic picture and then we're
taking this is
like the final say right this picture
this it's this response and we're done
with it but really looking at these
things as Dynamic processes right even
looking at One Singular image this is
not a one and done thing your
impressions change over time because
your eyes move because your
understanding changes um because that
understanding changes possibly where
you're looking so it also changes what
you're going to see Etc um and that to
me is a much more exciting and
interesting way of of looking at these
topics right it's really this Dynamic
unfolding process so yeah thanks for
mentioning that I think it's really
important cool and also I feel like it
puts
action kicking off the process like I'm
thinking of a food tasting like food is
put into your mouth and you can report
on it whereas if you have the
menu then the action kicks
off something that is later the
aesthetic exper you choose which museum
to go to you choose where to look and so
that kind of front loads this action
elements whereas in the contrived
setting the action elements may be
controlled by the
experimentor and the action that the
person took was to sign up for a study
which is still a kind of action but then
that doesn't like builds the kind of of
Arc that we
actually like you said paid money and
take time out of life to to
enjoy cool anything else you'd like to
add um I would like to add thank you um
for having me um said that very briefly
in the beginning but I think it's really
cool to have these conversations um I
think it's also nice to have it out
there in the open and I hope that I
didn't use all too much charagon um and
I would also like to mention that uh
people can very easily Google me by my
name and you should be very free to get
in touch with me if you're interested in
any of these things I'm sometimes busy
but always interested in talking with
people uh no matter what they where
they're coming
from awesome thank you again see you
next time thank
you for